A Finding Aid to the Dorothy Goldeen Gallery Records, 1961-1996, bulk 1987-1996, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dorogolg
Archives of American Art
Dorothy Goldeen Gallery records
bulk 1987-1996
1961-1996
AAA.dorogolg
Archives of American Art
4 Linear feet
The records of the southern California Dorothy Goldeen Gallery measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1961 to 1996, with the bulk of the items dating from 1987 to 1996. Included are artists' files and files on six group exhibitions. Artists files may include correspondence, printed material, resumes, slides, and photogaphs of art or artists.
Dorothy Goldeen Gallery. (Santa Monica, Calif.)
Scope and Contents note
The records of the southern California Dorothy Goldeen Gallery measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1961 to 1996, with the bulk of the items dating from 1987 to 1996. Included are artists' files and files on six group exhibitions. Artists' files may include correspondence, printed material, resumes, slides, and photogaphs of art or artists.
Artists particularly well-represented in the records include Ciel Bergman, Jo Ann Callis, Mary Campell, Michael Dvortscak, Heidi Fasnacht, Patsy Krebs, Terence La Noue, Ken Riddle, Lyn Bell Rose, Italo Scanga, Paul Tzanetopoulos, Daniel Weiner, John White, and Allee Willis, among others. There are gaps in the records and several well known artists that Goldeen showcased are not extensively documented.
Biographical/Historical note
The Dorothy Goldeen Gallery (1987-1996) was an art gallery in Santa Monica, California founded by Dorothy Goldeen.
Dorothy Goldeen's professional career began in 1973 in San Francisco with the Hansen Fuller Gallery which later became Fuller Goldeen Gallery. In 1987, Goldeen relocated to Los Angeles and opened the Dorothy Goldeen Gallery. Historically significant artists such as Magdalena Abakanowicz and Nam June Paik were represented as well as influential, emerging Los Angeles artists such as Diana Thater and Jennifer Steinkamp.
In 1996, after twenty-three years as a fine arts dealer, Goldeen closed her gallery and launched the Dorothy Goldeen Art Advisory in Santa Monica.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Artists Files, 1961-1996 (3.9 linear feet; Box 1-4)
Series 2: Group Exhibitions, 1988-1996 (0.1 linear feet; Box 4)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Dorothy Goldeen Gallery records were donated by Dorothy Golodeen to the Archives of American Art in 2003.
Bergman, Ciel, 1938-; Callis, Jo Ann, 1940-; Campbell, Mary; Dvortcsak, Michael, 1938-; Fasnacht, Heide, 1951-; Krebs, Patsy; La Noue, Terence; Riddle, Ken; Rose, Lyn; Scanga, Italo, 1932-; Tzanetopoulos, Paul; Weiner, Daniel; Willis, Allee; Art galleries, Commercial--California--Santa Monica; Photographs
- Artists Files, 1961-1996; Series 1; 3.9 Linear feet Box 1-4
  Arrangement note
  This series is filed alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents note
  Within this series are Dorothy Goldeen files relating to featured artists at the gallery. Of note are artist files on Magdalena Abakanowicz, Nam June Paik, and Brazilian painter, Beatriz Milhazes. Folders typically contain letters, exhibiton catalogs, resumes, slides, photogaphs of art or artists, and greeting cards.
  - Magdalena Abakanowicz, 1996; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William Allen, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carlos Almarez and Elsa Florez, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Altoon, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Joseph Amar, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert Arneson, 1992; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Charles Arnoldi, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Michael S. Bell, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Trevor Bell, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barbara Benish, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fletcher Benton, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Howard Bentre, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ciel Berman (aka Cheryl Bowers), 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rodger Berry, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cheryl Bowers (aka Ciel Berman), 1974-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Ellen Brooks, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chris Brown, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Matthew Brown, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grisha Bruskin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - John Buck, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Farideh Cadot, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - John Cage, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jo Ann Callis, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Mary Campell, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Squeak Carnwath, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lawrence Carroll, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dale Chihuly, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Duck-Hyun Cho, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tony Cragg, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Robert Cumming, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Erica Daborn, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ron Davis, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Stephan Davis, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Roy De Forest, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Stephan Destaeblar, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Sue Dirksen, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - James Drake, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Michael Dvortscak, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Fred Eerdekens, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sharon Ellis and Stefan Kurten, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Heide Fasnacht, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Joel Fisher, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Charles Gaines, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Vincent Gallo, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Steve Galloway, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Daniel Gendron, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Charles Ginnever, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Niel Goodman, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ann Hamilton, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Roger Hankins, 1987-1889 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - James Hansen, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Al Held, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bill Henson, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - David Hodges, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Darcy Huebler, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Frank Hyder, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oliver Jackson, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Craig Kaufman, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sheila Klein, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Paul Kos, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Leonard Koscianski, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Joyce Kozloff, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Patsy Krebs, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Erik Kreis, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Joseph Kreis, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cheryl Laemmle, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Terrence La Noue, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 26-33)
  - Terrence La Noue and Charles Ginnever, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Terrence La Noue and Dennis Leon, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Daniel Lavi, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Daniel Lavi and Kenneth Riddle, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Daniel Lavi and Kenneth Riddle and Zody Zellen, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Dennis Leon, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tony Ligamire, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Donald Lipski, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Frank Lobdell, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Paul Manes, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Annette Messager, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Beatriz Milhazes, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Robin Mitchell, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Martin Mull, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Christa Naher, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ross Neher, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Nam June Paik, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jurgen Partenheimer, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ed Paschke, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bill Plummer, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Janis Provisor, 1988-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Elsa Rady, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alan Rath and Russell Crotty, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Zizi Raymond and Adam Ross, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Beverly Rayner, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Scott Ricter, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kenneth Riddle, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lyn Bell Rose, 1987-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Adam Ross, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Richard Rothman, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Linda Roush, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Italo Scanga, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Anne Siems, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hassel Smith, 1961-1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - David Storey, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Larry Thomas, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Imants Tillers, 1976-1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Paul Tzansiopoulos, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Nelson Valentine, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Josefa Vaughan, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Gabriel Verdi, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - John White, 1963-1990 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
  - Daniel Wiener, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Suzy Willey, 1991-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Allee Willis, 1983-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Robin Winters, 1981-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Andrew Young, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Group Exhibitions, 1988-1996; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 4
  This series includes files related to group exhibitions at the gallery. Found here are notes and biographies on a jewelry show, as well as slides for the Fresh Visions exhibition. Folders may contain correspondence, photographs of art, invitations, posters and fliers, invoices, and price lists.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Private Reserve, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Fresh Visions I, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Fresh Visions II, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Poured Paintings, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Summer Group Show, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Jewelry Show, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - Multiple Parts, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - L.A. Current: Works on Paper, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)